# **GAURAV SOOD**

#### Sr. Data Scientist



**J** +91 9632714987

Bangalore, India

github.com/gsood-gaurav



"Senior Data Scientist with total 14 years of experience, and 7 years of experience in Machine Learning, developing open source software in Python, C++, contributing as both individual contributor and team leader, working on Machine Learning, conceptualizing, designing and implementing end to end solutions. Currently working on Natural Language Processing and Reinforcement Learning. Have used both traditional machine learning methods like Bayesian Networks, Conditional Random Fields and modern deep learning methods LSTMs, Transformer based models like BERT and GPT"

## **SKILLS**

Python PyTorch TensorFlow JAX Julia Flux NumPy SciPy Matplotlib						
Large Language Models Generative AI Probabilistic Modelling Reinforcement Learning	Open Source Software					
Communication Leadership Skills						

## EXPERIENCE

#### Sr. Data Scientist

#### HP Inc. June 2021 - Ongoing

- Bangalore, India
- Designed and Developed Large Language Models Based application for web content filtering acheiving a recall of 0.94
- Implemented evaluation scripts to benchmark LLM application's performance on accuracy, cost(token usage) and inference time comparing GPT4/GPT3.5/GPT-40-mini/GPT-40
- Mentored three data science interns on Hardware logs analysis using Graph Neural Networks and Large Language Models(GPT-2) achieving precision/recall of 0.85/0.73.
- Fine Tuned 4-bit quantized Small language Chat model on custom data set using QLORA acheiving an accuracy of 0.96
- Developed Telemetery data analysis pipline using Large Language Model embeddings, sentence transformers, UMAP, Variational AutoEncoder and HDBScan

Prompt Engineering	GPT2	FineTuning	Probabilistic Modelling	Leadership Skills	Graph Nerual Networks
Embedding Models					

### Software Engineer Machine Learning

## **HP Inc. June 2017 - 2021**

- **B**angalore, India
- Analyzed Sales Time Series Data (Short term/Long term forecasting) using Prophet, ARIMA, Gradient Boosting models, studying the effects of Consumer Price Index, WholeSale Price Index, Industrial Production Growth and employment, hyperparamter tuning using Optuna, producing a MAPE score of 6-8%.
- Worked on HP Personal Systems User Behavior Modelling using Tree Based Models, SHAP, UMAP, HDBScan for targeted market campaigning.
- Developed simulator environment for online Reinforcement Learning for automated hardware diagnostics.
- Developed Sequence Tagging Model using LSTMs for discovering insights in call center records acheiving a precision and recall score of 0.91/0.85
- Mentored 4 interns on sequence tagging using Conditional Random Fields to extract insights from call center records.
- Presented and communicated ideas around Probabilistic Modelling and Reinforecement Learning to senior leadership
- Analyzed Call center record using Bayesian Networks for predictive diagnostics as an aid to call center executives.

Time Series Analysis CART Reinforcement Learning Probabilistic Graphical Models Data Annotation

Senior Software Engineer

#### HP Inc. June 2015 - 2017

- Bangalore, India
- Designed and Developed a parser for PostScript Language to extract images and meta data which was impacting 50000 hp customers and saving 5 million dollars.
- Designed and developed Telemetery module in python.
- Led team of 7 software developers designing and implementing open source software used by over 1 million customers.
- · Worked on understanding PDF specification, design and implemented PDF document processing using PDF libraries like iText and PDFium
- Lead a team of six people which delived Imaging Processing Solutions using Python Imaging Library, TessaractOCT to over 10 PSU banks in india

OpenSource Sofware Algorithms **Image Processing** Leadership Skills

## Software Engineer

#### HP Inc. June 2010 - 2015

- Bangalore, India
- Designed and Implemented Telemetry module in python using asyncio.
- Led team of 7 software developers designing and implementing open source software used by over 1 million customers.
- Collaborated with customers and stakeholders, gathering requirements and communicating constraints.
- Developed UI, backend, modules in Python for the hp's open source imaging solution (https://developers.hp.com/ hp-linux-imaging-and-printing)

Python | Open Source Software Asynchronous Programming

# CERTIFICATIONS

Deep Learning Specialization

Coursera Oct-2021 Credential ID G8PG2GY6WFS)

Reinforcement Learning Specialization

Coursera Sept-2021 Credential IDD3LDNU8BRW68

Introduction to Quantum Computing Coursera May-2021 Credential ID RXQHLEC2WYC8

## PREVENTIVE DISCLOSURES

- Gaurav Sood, Ranjith Kumar Gopa, Nandan Kumar Nidhi(May 2024) "Representing Tabular Data using Large Lanugage Models" https://www.tdcommons.org/dpubs\_series/6998/
- Gaurav Sood (Feb 2021) "A Reinforcement Learning Approach to Printer Diagnostics" https://www.tdcommons.org/ dpubs\_series/4244/
- Gaurav Sood, Pavleen Kaur Brar, Raghu Anantharangachar (April 2019) "Sequence Prediction for Print/Scan Issues using Bayesian Networks" https://www.tdcommons.org/dpubs\_series/2117/

# **EDUCATION**

Msc Research Speech Recoginition Indian Institute of Science Bangalore 2006-2009

Speech Recognition using Support Vector Machines

**BTech Electronics and Communication Engg** 

**GNE Ludhiana 2001-2005**